Guide to the Louis Golding Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Louis Golding papers
1911-1953
GEN MSS 77
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.25
(7 boxes)
The papers contain manuscripts, notes, correspondence, and other papers pertaining to the five-volume series Tales of the Silver Sisters.
Golding, Louis, 1895-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Philip Neufeld, 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
LOUIS GOLDING (1895-1958)
Louis Golding was one of the most successful Anglo-Jewish authors of post-World War I England. He was born in Manchester of Jewish parents who had recently emigrated from Cherkassy, in the Ukrainian Soviet Union. After graduating from Manchester Grammar School, Golding won a scholarship to Queen's College, Oxford. His education was interrupted by World War I, but he later returned to college and began writing. Golding spent the next years of his life traveling extensively in the Mediterranean and Near East.
Golding is probably best known for his novels Magnolia Street (1932) and the five-volume series Tales of the Silver Sisters, also know as the Doomington Saga, novels that examine twentieth-century Jewish life in Western Europe. Golding's nonfiction works include The Jewish Problem (1938), Hitler Through the Ages (1939), travel books, and a study of James Joyce. He co-authored the dramatization of Magnolia Street performed in 1934. In 1944, Mr. Emmanuel, one of the Doomington novels, was made into a film. Although Golding never produced an autobiography, he wrote about his own life in his commentary on current events The World I Knew (1940).
Golding married Anne Wintrobe in 1956, two years before his death.
Scope and Contents
The Louis Golding Papers contain manuscripts, notes, correspondence, and other papers pertaining to the five volume series Tales of the Silver Sisters. The papers span the years 1911 to 1953, but the bulk of them cover the years 1932-1952, the period in which he wrote the Doomington Saga.
Golding's manuscripts are arranged in publication order, with notes and other related material accompanying each novel: Five Silver Daughters (1934), Mr. Emmanuel (1939), The Glory of Elsie Silver (1945), The Dangerous Places (1951), To the Quayside (1953). The collection contains a holograph manuscript of each book except Mr. Emmanuel. There are research notes, outlines, preliminary drafts, or publicity material for all of the novels except The Glory of Elsie Silver. These papers document Golding's method of conception and the reception of his published works.
The research material for Five Silver Daughters is organized by subjects reflecting the themes of the novel. Information on post-World War I Russia includes the memoirs of a German soldier who was captured by the Russians but escaped in the chaos of the Revolution. Notes on the British cloth trade, post-World War I world economy, and high finance fraud relate to the business aspects of the plot. Two short stories represent an early form of the novel's subject matter.
A September 1933 issue of Der Stürmer (Box 6, folder 72) is a background item for Mr. Emmanuel. Documentation on the reception of the book includes letters from friends and colleagues congratulating Golding, commenting on the book, or thanking him for presentation copies. There is some business correspondence with agents and one letter of complaint from a bookseller about a Foyle's Book Club edition. Material about the film version of Mr. Emmanuel (1944) includes a pamphlet advertising the movie and a series of stills arranged by numbers, probably provided by Golding.
The research material for The Dangerous Places includes firsthand accounts of Eastern European Jews who survived the destruction of the ghettos. Various preliminary drafts precede the final version.
To the Quayside, the final novel, has little accompanying material, aside from preliminary notes showing the development of the book. A handwritten piece called "Goodbye to Elsie Silver," Golding's overview of the series, can be found with publicity material.
The Louis Golding Papers document the creation of the Doomington Saga and contain important information on modern Jewish history.
Jews in literature; Jews -- Segregation; Jews -- Poland -- Warsaw; Jews, East European; Jews, Russian; Judaism -- History -- Modern period, 1750-; Soviet Union -- History -- Revolution, 1917-1921; Authors; Golding, Louis, 1895-1958
- Five Silver Daughters, 1932-33
  - General notes and background material, 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Oversize, Box 6, folder 69
  - Memoir of German prisoner of war in Russia, 1916-[18?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Material re: British-Russian military service 1917, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    See also: Oversize, Box 6, folder 70
  - Notes and Correspondence
    - 1917 Russian Revolution, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Russian revolutionaries, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - British cloth manufacture, post- World War I, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Post-World War I world economy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      See also: Oversize, Box 69, folder 71
    - High finance fraud, 1932-33 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Short stories used for novel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10-17)
  - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Notes on manuscript
    - Golding's notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Reviews of manuscript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Mr. Emmanuel, n.d.
  - General notes and background material (Box 2, Folder 23)
    See also: Oversize, Box 69, folder 72
  - Correspondence, 1939, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Book publicity material, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Movie publicity material, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Movie stills
    - Numbered stills, [ca. 1944] (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
    - Unnumbered and autograph stills, [ca. 1944] (Box 2, Folder 30)
- The Glory of Elsie Silver, n.d.
  - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31-38)
- The Dangerous Places
  - Notes
    - General notes and background material (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Hungary, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 40)
      See also: Oversize, Box 69, folder 73
    - Poland (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Slovakia, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
      See also: Oversize, Box 69, folder 74
  - Drafts and scenarios (Box 4, Folder 43)
    See also: Oversize, Box 69, folder 75
  - Holograph manuscript, 1949-50 (Box 4, Folder 44-53)
  - Notes on manuscript, [1950?] (Box 4, Folder 54)
- To the Quayside, n.d.
  - Notes and outline (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - First draft, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Holograph manuscript, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 57-66)
  - Publicity material, [ca. 1953] (Box 5, Folder 67)
- Miscellaneous, n.d.
  - Papers, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68)
- Oversize, 1932-33
  - General notes and background material, 1932-33 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Material re: British-Russian military service 1917, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Post-World War I world economy, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - General notes and background material (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Hungary, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Slovakia, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Drafts and scenarios (Box 6, Folder 75)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Box 7, Restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals and the material is arranged in folder order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 1, 1932, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 76-77)
  - Box 1, folder 4, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Box 1, folder 7, 1933 May 20 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Box 1, folder 8, [ca. 1933] (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Box 2, folder 23, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Box 2, folder 24, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Box 2, folder 25, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Box 4, folder 39, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Box 4, folder 43, 1950 Jan 30 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Box 5, folder 55, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Box 5, folder 67, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 87)